Since 2009, I have desperately tried to explain that a Great Transatlantic Market was in preparation.
It is a market between the USA and the EU. It has become quite commonplace now, we know what it consists in.
Why am I the only one here who wrote that there was a project of a Great Transatlantic Market in his draft, in 2009?
A few months ago, the European Parliament voted, socialists included,
that indeed, there would be a great deregulated, duty-free transatlantic market,
that would remove trade barriers on capitals and goods.
Were you aware of that ? No, you were not!
And now they're all waking up, after they voted everytime that something had to be voted,
and all of a sudden, they say it's very dangerous etc. Well they should have done that before!
Most of our fellow citizens are not aware of it.
It is called the Great Transatlantic Market.
You and I are all in this together.
In 2015, we will all be part of the same socio-economic union with the USA,
and no one ever says a word about it anywhere!
I condemn this treaty, of course.
Someone had a lot of common sense when he said that no one asked for it.
I do not support the development of the Great Transatlantic Treaty
that will remove all custom barriers in 2015.
This treaty will deteriorate the social rights of French and European workers as never before
because they will be based on the social and labor rights of the USA.
Millions of jobs will be destroyed on both sides of the Atlantic.
In this common market, economic and environmental standards will be on the same level, the lowest of course, in Europe and in the USA.
Let me give you a concrete example.
North Americans wash their chickens with chlorine, so you'll eat chlorine-treated chicken.
North Americans despise Protected Designations of Origin, and more particularly regional designations.
They already devastated everything in their country, so they don't even understand what we are talking about.
Tomorrow, you will drink Chablis wine from Mississippi and Champagne from Oklahoma.
This is in the treaty!
We need to implement solidarity-based protectionism,
which means we won't allow some goods to enter the country because we are capable of producing them.
It is more rational to produce them by ourselves rather than import them from the other side of the planet..
Until now, when a dispute occurred between a big company and a country that had certain laws,
the case was judged by this country's justice.
But now, with this agreement, such cases will be judged by private arbitral tribunals.
Arbitral tribunals modify geopolitical balances of power
since nations will lose importance compared to companies and investors, that will no longer be under the authority of common law.
[We have been spied on] And after that, we learned that Americans spy on us.
You should stop negotiating since we the Europeans have been spied on while we were preparing our discussion papers.
In January 2013, Barack Obama backed the idea,
and his lapdogs showed up immediately to ask where to sign.
Ftançois Hollande, the President of the Republic, never said a word about it anywhere,
and now he signs an editorial column in Le Monde (newspaper) with Mr Obama
in order to say TAFTA is an opportunity, and that they should hurry because people might be scared.
[Some people never talk about it] If this treaty is such a good thing, why did Mr Hollande say nothing about TAFTA during his campaign?
[Mélenchon regularly talks about it] Where are our freedom and our sovereignty
when you never say a word about it in any assembly or any meeting,
when month after month you've been secretly planning what you call the Great Transatlantic Market, by voting in collusion with one another?
I solemnly commit myself to never voting any liberalization measure whatsoever, under any circumstances.
On no account will I ever vote the Great Transatlantic Market with the USA.
In 2017, the USA and Europe will complete their common market project.
No one will ask your opinion on this treaty. No one will ask what the people thinks about it.
This is why I stand as a candidate in the 2017 presidential election,
because it will enable you to make a decision on the matter by voting.
I absolutely condemn this agreement. I hope it will be a failure, and I will do everything I can to hinder it.
Against TAFTA, the solution is Mélenchon.